<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>motorStats.io</title><link>http://localhost:1313/</link><description>Recent content on motorStats.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What's Up With All Those DNFs in the Hybrid Era?</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/hybrid-era-reliability/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/hybrid-era-reliability/</guid><description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/posts/hybrid-era-reliability/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post What's Up With All Those DNFs in the Hybrid Era?" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a class="link" href="https://motorstats.io/posts/how-competitive-hybrid-era/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we explored how competitive the racing was in different technical eras of the DW12 chassis. What we found is that the Hybrid Era brought the tightest and most competitive racing of the last decade. This led to some real guilt&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on my part. There are a lot of hybrid haters out there, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to ruin anyone&amp;rsquo;s off-season by suggesting that IndyCar in its current state might be good and fun to watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily - at least for the hybrid haters - we did come across one metric that really made the hybrid look bad. Cars were finishing races at a much lower rate in the Hybrid Era than during any of the previous decade of the DW12 Chassis. After shamelessly suggesting the hybrid has given us good racing, the least I can do is take a deep dive into this low reliability number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="dnfs-across-eras"&gt;DNFs Across Eras
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;First: a quick refresher on the 4 eras we looked at for the DW12 chassis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;2015 to 2017&lt;/em&gt; - Each engine manufacturer provided their own Aero kit. No aeroscreen or hybrid power unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;2018 to 2019&lt;/em&gt; - All cars used the same aero kit. No aeroscreen and no hybrid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;2020 to June 2024&lt;/em&gt; - Aeroscreen is introduced. Spec aero still in place. No hybrid power unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hybrid&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;July 2024 to 2025&lt;/em&gt; - Hybrid power unit is introduced. Spec aero and aeroscreen still in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is actually a 5th era of the DW12 chassis: from 2012-2014 when the chassis was new but before the OEM aerokit was implemented. But, the data for this era is incomplete – especially in 2012 – so it&amp;rsquo;s being excluded from this analysis.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we&amp;rsquo;ve defined these 4 eras, let&amp;rsquo;s refresh on DNF&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; rates for each year since the start of the OEM Aero Era:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe
src="http://localhost:1313/plots/DnfByYearEra.html"
title="DNF Rate by Year and Era"
loading="lazy"
style="width:100%;height:525px;border:0;"
&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2nd half of 2024, which was the first (partial) season of the Hybrid Era, had historically high DNF rates. Things got better in 2025, but DNFs in 2025 were still higher than any single season of the Aeroscreen or Spec Aero Eras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="tight-racing-vs-unreliable-cars"&gt;Tight Racing vs Unreliable Cars
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most obvious question we can ask regarding these DNFs is &amp;ldquo;why?&amp;rdquo; Maybe the answer actually lies in our previous post. Tight racing means a bunched-up field, with more opportunities for drivers to make mistakes that lead to contact with another car. If that&amp;rsquo;s the case, I&amp;rsquo;d argue a higher DNF rate is not a bad thing (at least from the fan&amp;rsquo;s perspective).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we&amp;rsquo;re seeing more mechanical failures, however, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel good for the sport. This would support the hybrid haters&amp;rsquo; narrative that the DW12 chassis can&amp;rsquo;t handle all this weight and that&amp;rsquo;s causing an unprecedented number of mechincal failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So which is it? To answer this question, we can go back to those trusty &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.imscdn.com/INDYCAR/Documents/6460/2025-05-26/indycar-race-results.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;results pdfs&lt;/a&gt; that IndyCar publishes after each race. Race results will list a &lt;em&gt;Reason Out&lt;/em&gt; for any car that is not running at the end of the race. From 2015-2025, each of these reasons appeared at least once:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;: A car collides with another car or the wall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mechanical&lt;/strong&gt;: A mechanical failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Off Course&lt;/strong&gt;: The car leaves the track (as a result of racing/driver error, not a mechanical error) and is unable to return to the track.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handling&lt;/strong&gt;: The car is still running but is retired due to becoming undriveable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retired&lt;/strong&gt;: A generic retirement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DQ&lt;/strong&gt;: The car is disqualified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electrical&lt;/strong&gt;: An electrical problem—which I guess IndyCar didn&amp;rsquo;t want to lump into &amp;ldquo;mechanical&amp;rdquo; problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNS&lt;/strong&gt;: Did not start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Pits&lt;/strong&gt;: The car is physically pitted when the race ends - most likely due to some kind of issue that didn&amp;rsquo;t lead to a full retirement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fire&lt;/strong&gt;: Um&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/posts/hybrid-era-reliability/fire3.png"
width="600"
height="300"
srcset="http://localhost:1313/posts/hybrid-era-reliability/fire3_hu_c40f4d620184afe9.png 480w, http://localhost:1313/posts/hybrid-era-reliability/fire3_hu_d591f5597070bede.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="An Example of a “Fire” DNF"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="200"
data-flex-basis="480px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these classifications are more common than others, and they do seem to change over time as well. Here is how often each classification was used in each era:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Contact&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Mechanical&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Off Course&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Handling&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Retired&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;DQ&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Electrical&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;DNS&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;In Pits&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Fire&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;123&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;78&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;194&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;Hybrid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the vast majority of DNFs are classified as either Contact or Mechanical. Off Course has come up a couple dozen times&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, but the remaining 7 classifications are rare, appearing at most a handful of times in one or two eras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rare categories aren&amp;rsquo;t going to be very useful towards determining whether the DNFs are due to tight racing or less reliable cars, but we can reasonably group them into broader categories: Contact and Off Course should go together, as these can reasonably be attributed to tight racing, overly aggressive driving, or things of that nature. We&amp;rsquo;ll call this group &amp;ldquo;crashes&amp;rdquo;. Mechanical, Electrical, and Fire can all be lumped together into a category called &amp;ldquo;car failures&amp;rdquo;. Handling, Retired, DQ, DNS, and In Pits are all pretty rare and are all difficult to cleanly attribute to either car failure or tight competition, so we&amp;rsquo;ll lump those into a cop-out &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo; category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll call the rate at which cars DNF due to a crash reason as &lt;em&gt;crash rate&lt;/em&gt; and the rate at which cars DNF due to a car failure as &lt;em&gt;car failure rate&lt;/em&gt;. We aren&amp;rsquo;t going to spend a lot of time on &lt;em&gt;other rate&lt;/em&gt; (sorry), but the sum of all 3 of these we will call &lt;em&gt;DNF rate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now that we&amp;rsquo;ve defined some metrics for a more digestible 3 categories, we can look at the trend by year and see what is contributing to DNFs. If we see a spike in crash rate, then we can blame the tight racing. If we see a spike in car failure rate, we&amp;rsquo;ll conclude the hybrid broke everything. If we see a spike in other rate, I&amp;rsquo;m taking my ball and going home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe
src="http://localhost:1313/plots/DnfRateByYearType.html"
title="DNF Rate by Year and DNF Type"
loading="lazy"
style="width:100%;height:525px;border:0;"
&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crash DNFs are up by a lot in the hybrid half of 2024, but they go back down to average or slightly below average in 2025. Mechanical failures are above average for both seasons of the Hybrid Era, though they are in line with the aeroscreen half of 2024, as well as the entire OEM Aero Era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="statistical-significance"&gt;Statistical Significance
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s our conclusion? If you have an annoying stats friend, or are yourself someone&amp;rsquo;s annoying stats friend, then the &amp;ldquo;small sample size&amp;rdquo; alarm bells might be going off in your head right now. The super high crash rate in the hybrid half of 2024 came in only 9 races. The Hybrid Era as a whole is only 26 races old. It&amp;rsquo;s actually quite common for numbers to look inflated in small sample sizes but to even out as the sample size gets larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So before we draw any conclusions, we should determine if our sample sizes are large enough for a given number to be meaningful, or if it&amp;rsquo;s just a product of statistical noise. This is what tests of statistical significance are for.&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:5" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We compare one set of outcomes (such as DNF rate in the Hybrid Era) vs a benchmark set of outcomes (such as DNFs for the entire rest of our sample set), and if the two populations are different enough (as determined by their means and standard deviations), we can deem the populations to be statistically significant&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:6" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, time for the results. I&amp;rsquo;ve run a handful of different tests below. Each test asks whether a certain statistic (DNF rate, crash rate, etc.) is statistically significant over a certain period of time (either the entire Hybrid Era or the hybrid half of 2024). A p-value of .05 or lower is considered statistically significant. Here are the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Test&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;p-value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Significant&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DNF Rate in Hybrid Era&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.049&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;Barely&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Crash Rate in Hybrid Era&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.231&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Crash Rate in 2024 (Hybrid half)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.020&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Car Failure Rate in Hybrid Era&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.202&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Car Failure Rate in 2024 (Hybrid half)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.210&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So technically, the higher DNF rate in the Hybrid Era is statistically significant at the 5% level. But if we break it down, the only number that is comfortably statistically significant is the crash rate in the hybrid half of 2024. Basically, this means something was going on in the 2nd half of 2024 that was leading to more contact. Perhaps – and I&amp;rsquo;m just spitballing here – the field was getting used to a newer, heavier power unit that was introduced halfway into the season and, as a result, made more mistakes. After some time to get used to the new power unit, however, those contact DNFs went back to normal in the 2025 season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does this say about the theory that tighter racing led to more DNFs? Probably bunk. What does this say about the hybrid haters&amp;rsquo; theory that the worse, heavier car led to more car failures? Also largely bunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, it looks like it&amp;rsquo;s a third thing: namely a major mid-season rule change that led to an adjustment period for drivers and brought more contact. But once the field adjusted, it was racing as usual. And what about the future? Well, if the car failure rate isn&amp;rsquo;t statistically significant, and the crash rate went back to normal in 2025, then there&amp;rsquo;s no reason to think we&amp;rsquo;ll see a substantially higher rate of DNFs persist going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover photo by &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/@srz" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;sydney Rae&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-black-and-white-photo-of-a-race-car-on-a-track-nLotmcNQ5G0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author may or may not be Catholic&amp;hellip;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For convenience&amp;rsquo;s sake, let&amp;rsquo;s just assume the data from this missing era supports whatever you personally think is true about the racing in IndyCar. That&amp;rsquo;s great news for the hybrid haters, who just found 3 years of data that confirms unequivocally that the Hybrid Era ruined our sport! (People who don&amp;rsquo;t mind the Hybrid Era please ignore the previous sentence.)&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IndyCar doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to use the term &amp;ldquo;DNF&amp;rdquo; in any of their official publications. Instead they tend to say a car is &amp;ldquo;out&amp;rdquo; as in &amp;ldquo;out of the race&amp;rdquo;. This makes some sense given that IndyCar awards points to every car that runs the race, even if they are out after 1 lap. But also it&amp;rsquo;s kind of annoying, and as a former baseball writer, I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like writing about &amp;ldquo;outs&amp;rdquo; anymore. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to stick to using &amp;ldquo;DNF&amp;rdquo;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, there has not been a single Off Course DNF in the Hybrid Era. This actually makes sense as the Hybrid Era is the first time that a car can be restarted from the cockpit. In previous eras, if you went off the track and the car stalled/the engine died, you were done. But with the hybrid, you can turn the car back on and drive back onto the course. RIP Off Course.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Warning: the following footnote contains a nerdy rant about frequentist statistics. Non-nerds should proceed with caution.&lt;/em&gt;] A lot of people tend to think that &amp;ldquo;statistical significance&amp;rdquo; is some kind of magic threshold that makes your data unquestionably correct. In reality, tests for statistical significance essentially just give us a probability that one number is not meaningfully different from a different number. Anything under 5% (i.e. a 95% probability that the numbers are meaningfully different) is typically thought of as being statistically significant, but that&amp;rsquo;s a completely arbitrary number. For instance, if we were talking about driver safety, 5% is WAY too high of a threshold. If, on the other hand, we&amp;rsquo;re asking a question about reliability in the Hybrid Era, and the answer is most likely going to be used only in the context of a bar argument, then 5% is probably fine.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:5" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;WARNING: An even nerdier discussion is coming in this footnote. Seriously, if you are the type of person who enjoys having friends or ever having another conversation with a member of the opposite sex, I highly advise you skip ahead.&lt;/em&gt;] It&amp;rsquo;s also worth mentioning that tests for statistical significance are based on a certain set of assumptions that rarely describe the real world, namely the assumption that each individual outcome is an &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent_and_identically_distributed_random_variables" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;independent and identically distributed random variable&lt;/a&gt;. Mechanical DNFs sort of meet this criteria, but contact DNFs really don&amp;rsquo;t, as &amp;ldquo;contact&amp;rdquo; is often with another car and therefore not independent. For that reason, we&amp;rsquo;re definitely going to treat any number at or near the 5% threshold with some skepticism.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:6" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Contact Us</title><link>http://localhost:1313/contact/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 23:55:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/contact/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;d love to hear from you. Use the form below to send us a message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="contact-form"&gt;
&lt;form action="https://formspree.io/f/xpqwblgw" method="POST"&gt;
&lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
&lt;label for="name"&gt;Your name:&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type="text" id="name" name="name" class="form-control" required&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
&lt;label for="email"&gt;Your email:&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input type="email" id="email" name="email" class="form-control" required&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
&lt;label for="message"&gt;Your message:&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;textarea id="message" name="message" rows="6" class="form-control" required&gt;&lt;/textarea&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;button type="submit" class="btn btn-primary"&gt;Send Message&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.contact-form {
max-width: 600px;
margin: 2rem auto;
padding: 1.5rem;
background: #f8f9fa;
border-radius: 8px;
}
.form-group {
margin-bottom: 1.5rem;
}
.form-group label {
display: block;
margin-bottom: 0.5rem;
font-weight: 600;
}
.form-control {
width: 100%;
padding: 0.75rem;
border: 1px solid #ced4da;
border-radius: 4px;
font-size: 1.75rem;
line-height: 1.5;
}
textarea.form-control {
min-height: 150px;
}
.btn {
display: inline-block;
padding: 0.75rem 2rem;
background-color: #d91a20;
color: white;
border: none;
border-radius: 4px;
cursor: pointer;
font-size: 1.1rem;
font-weight: 600;
text-decoration: none;
transition: all 0.2s ease;
text-transform: uppercase;
letter-spacing: 0.5px;
}
.btn:hover {
background-color: #b7151a;
transform: translateY(-1px);
box-shadow: 0 2px 8px rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.15);
}
&lt;/style&gt;</description></item><item><title>How Bad (or Good) was the Racing in the Hybrid Era?</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-competitive-hybrid-era/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/how-competitive-hybrid-era/</guid><description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/posts/how-competitive-hybrid-era/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post How Bad (or Good) was the Racing in the Hybrid Era?" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the hybrid was introduced last July at Mid-Ohio, the public perception has been all about weight. Drivers, fans, the media, your uncle Bill - everyone agrees the Dallara DW12 was never designed to carry that much weight, and the racing has suffered as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not all the hybrid&amp;rsquo;s fault, of course - the aeroscreen added a bunch of weight long before the hybrid got here. But the combination of the two is just too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just look at the last lap of the Indy 500 this year compared to the last lap last year. Last year, without the hybrid, we got a dramatic back straight overtake that decided the race and somehow led to everyone liking Pato O&amp;rsquo;Ward more while cementing Josef Newgarden as an even bigger villain. This year? Sure there was a close battle for P1 on the last lap, but where was the dramatic overtake? Also, unlike last year, only one of the two guys battling for first was in all those Fox commercials. Clearly the hybrid sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except this is a data blog, and IndyCar has thousands of laps of racing every year. A two-lap sample maybe feels like not enough data to draw a definitive conclusion. So let&amp;rsquo;s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="margin-of-victory"&gt;Margin of Victory.
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Margin of Victory&lt;/strong&gt; (MoV) - basically the time gap between P1 and P2 at the end of the race - seems to be the go-to metric whenever someone wants to cite how close the racing is. In fact, this post was inspired by an interview IndyCar&amp;rsquo;s Managing Director of Engine Development Darren Sansom gave on the &lt;a class="link" href="https://evergreenpodcasts.com/pit-pass-indy/the-67th-daytona-500-with-josef-newgarden-nascar-president-steve-phelps-and-IndyCar-spring-training-with-darren-sansum-IndyCar-managing-director-of-engine-development" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Pit Pass Indy podcast&lt;/a&gt;. In it, Mr. Sansom specifically cites a low average MoV in the Hybrid Era as evidence that the Hybrid hasn&amp;rsquo;t ruined the racing. (Interview starts around 16:14 mark).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously we already know he&amp;rsquo;s wrong and that the hybrid &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; ruined the racing, but let&amp;rsquo;s check those numbers just in case&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we crunch numbers on the Hybrid Era, though, we need something to compare to. The simplest approach would be to just break things into Hybrid vs Not-Hybrid. If we&amp;rsquo;re worried about weight, though, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t we also break things up by before/after aeroscreen was added? After all, the aeroscreen added close to 20 pounds before the hybrid ever showed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so now we have 3 distinct eras: (in reverse chronological order) the Hybrid Era, the Aeroscreen (non-hybrid) Era and the um&amp;hellip; Wait what do we call the era before the aeroscreen was introduced. The only good way to name this period is to look backwards another 3 years so we can capture yet another major tech change - specifically when each engine manufacturer brought its own aero kit from 2015-2017.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool, so we now have 4 distinct eras (with names!) we can use for our analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;2015 to 2017&lt;/em&gt; - Each engine manufacturer provided their own Aero kit. No aeroscreen or hybrid power unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;2018 to 2019&lt;/em&gt; - All cars used the same aero kit. No aeroscreen and no hybrid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;2020 to June 2024&lt;/em&gt; - Aeroscreen is introduced. Spec aero still in place. No hybrid power unit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hybrid&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;July 2024 to 2025&lt;/em&gt; - Hybrid power unit is introduced. Spec aero and aeroscreen still in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that cleared up, here&amp;rsquo;s what Margin of Victory looked like in each of the 4 eras above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;# of Races&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Median&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Largest&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;72&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hybrid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By average (and max) MoV, the Hybrid Era did indeed have the tightest racing. Meanwhile, the Spec Aero Era actually had the largest MoV of any era despite being lighter than both the Aeroscreen Era and Hybrid Era cars. We have done capital-S Science and determined that heavier cars lead to better racing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lead-lap-analysis"&gt;Lead Lap Analysis
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You – the clever reader of this blog – might be saying to yourself: &amp;ldquo;Not so fast! Margin of Victory only looks at the winning and runner-up cars. How is looking at two cars per race a good metric when there are 27+ cars in the field?&amp;rdquo; You&amp;rsquo;re right, oh wise reader. What if we looked at the margin between all the cars in the field?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK that&amp;rsquo;s actually more complex than it seems. You can&amp;rsquo;t determine gap between 2 cars that finish on different laps. So first let&amp;rsquo;s just analyze cars that finish on the lead lap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Percent of Cars on Lead Lap&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average Gap Lead Lap Only&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;63.5%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;59.3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;62.5%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hybrid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;58.3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gap&lt;/strong&gt; here is simply the gap to the car in front at the end of the race. Fewer cars are finishing on the lead lap in the Hybrid era, but those that do are racing closer to each other than in any other era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 2 reasons that we might be seeing a smaller percentage of cars finishing on the lead lap. Either fewer cars are finishing overall, or there is a wider gap between the front and back of the pack. Looking at the percentage of cars that finish, plus the average laps down for non-lead-lap finishers, helps shed some light on which of these possibilities is more liekly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Percent of Cars Finished&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Percent of Finishers on Lead Lap&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average Laps Down (Finishers Only)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;82.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;76.6%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;85.7%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;69.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;85.4%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;73.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hybrid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;81.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;71.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another mixed bag. On the one hand, the cars that finish on the lead lap are in a tighter race in the Hybrid Era than in any other era. On the other hand, fewer finishers are finishing on the lead lap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah, and a LOT fewer cars are finishing at all. Like 29% fewer than in the Aeroscreen era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of you pre-disposed to hate the hybrid I&amp;rsquo;m sure are licking your chops at that low finishing percentage. I promise we&amp;rsquo;ll look into it, but not in this post. Come on, we&amp;rsquo;re trying to define how &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; the racing is, and races aren&amp;rsquo;t judged on how many cars finish, they&amp;rsquo;re judged on what the cars that finish actually do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-entire-field"&gt;The Entire Field
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;So with all of that in mind what else do we want to know? For starters, how close is the racing between cars not on the lead lap? Also what about overtakes, we haven&amp;rsquo;t even looked at a car&amp;rsquo;s ability to move through the pack yet, and that feels important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah you&amp;rsquo;re right, those things do feel important, and we should look into it. So we&amp;rsquo;re going to define another metric that will do just that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Position Movement&lt;/strong&gt; (PMov) is as the absolute difference beteween a car&amp;rsquo;s starting and finishing position. For example, say the car on pole finished in 3rd and the car that started 5th won, then the Position Movement for the pole sitter would be 2 and the position movement for the winner would be 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average Position Movement&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average Gap (seconds)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hybrid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a surface level, overtaking looks to be strong in the Hybrid Era with cars moving through the pack much more than in any other era. Gap isn&amp;rsquo;t so great, but that might just be explained by faster cars getting around and moving past slower cars more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d love to put a bow on thigs and declare the Hybrid Era racing &amp;ldquo;pretty good&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but I can&amp;rsquo;t ignore all the hybrid haters out there just yet. Remember that finishing % number you read like 30 seconds ago? Remember how bad it was? Turns out cars have a really easy time moving through the pack when nearly 20% of the field ends up retiring early. So that PMov number is almost definitely inflated by DNFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also do we really care about the gap between cars 3 laps down? For that matter, do we care whether a car is 20 or 25 seconds behind the car in front of it? I mean I don&amp;rsquo;t, and I&amp;rsquo;m the one writing this blog. So let&amp;rsquo;s fix it, but how?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I pause to address those of you who follow analytics in other sports: right now you&amp;rsquo;re probably thinking to yourself, &amp;ldquo;Hey, I&amp;rsquo;m 10 minutes into reading this blog and I haven&amp;rsquo;t been introdued to a single made-up metric yet. So far everything we&amp;rsquo;ve talked about has just been number crunching from &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.imscdn.com/IndyCar/Documents/5498/6456/IndyCar-race-results.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;IndyCar results pdfs&lt;/a&gt;. Where are the 7-letter acronyms? Where is the confusing math that turns off casual fans but makes me, the analytics enthusiast, feel smarter?&amp;rdquo; Well, if that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for then you&amp;rsquo;re in luck. Nerd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for those of you who are just IndyCar fans desperately looking for any offseason content, I promise I won&amp;rsquo;t be &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; obnoxious with the math and you&amp;rsquo;ll walk away with some decent insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="finisher-adjusted-metrics"&gt;Finisher-Adjusted Metrics
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ok, with that out of the way, let&amp;rsquo;s get back to the DNF problem. I follow IndyCar for the racing and the strategy, not for the attrition. I&amp;rsquo;m guessing the same is true of the majority of my readers. So let&amp;rsquo;s find a way to measure how much cars move through the field based on speed and strategy, not just because cars in front of them DNFed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one&amp;rsquo;s actually pretty easy. If we re-sort the starting grid to exclude the cars that DNF, we can calculate position movement from the on-track racing and not from attrition. To explain, let&amp;rsquo;s revisit my earlier example where the pole sitter finishes 3rd and SP5 wins the race. Now let&amp;rsquo;s say that the car that started SP2 has a mechanical failure and DNFs. In this scenario, we would adjust the starting position of cars 3-27 by 1. So the pole sitter still has a position movement of 2 (since they started in front of the DNFing car) while the winner now has a position movement of 3 (since they ultimately passed the cars in SP4, SP3 and SP1 due to speed/strategy). We&amp;rsquo;ll call this &lt;strong&gt;Adjusted Position Movement&lt;/strong&gt; (adjPMov).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey look, a 7-letter metric! Though technically not an acornym.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average PMov&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Average adjPMov&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hybrid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One: adjusting for DNFs makes a huge difference. Two: Even when we account for DNFs, the Hybrid Era still has the most Position Movement of any other era. More interestingly, perhaps, the two eras of heavier cars have tighter racing than the two eras that preceed them. Maybe our joke conclusion of &amp;ldquo;heavier cars lead to better racing&amp;rdquo; might have actually been correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="improving-upon-gap-metrics"&gt;Improving upon Gap Metrics
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Addressing the gap issue also requires a little creativity. If the first 10 cars in a race each finish half a second in front of the next car, then P11 finishes 106 seconds ahead of P12, that&amp;rsquo;s an average gap of 10 seconds per car. 10 seconds per car sounds like a boring race but clearly is not given that P1 and P11 are only separated by 5 seconds. By the same token, a race where every car finishes 10 seconds ahead of the car in front kind of is a boring race. What we need to capture is how many cars finish a competitive distance behind the car they are chasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s define any gap of 3 seconds or less between two cars as a competitive distance. 3 seconds is a little arbitrary, and certainly we&amp;rsquo;ll want to do some of that capital-S Science later on to refine this number. But for now, 3 seconds feels like a small enough gap that a car could feasibly overtake within a few laps but not so small as to exclude most of the field. When a car finishes within 3 seconds of the car in front, we&amp;rsquo;ll call it a &lt;strong&gt;Position at Stake&lt;/strong&gt; (at Stake) and we can get a sense of how competitive an era is by calculating what percentage of positions are at stake (at Stake %) across an entire era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait! One more thing before we crunch those numbers. We haven&amp;rsquo;t really addressed the problem of &amp;ldquo;how excited are we really going to get over a competitive battle for P23?&amp;rdquo; I mean I&amp;rsquo;d rather P23 and P24 finish 1 second apart vs 30 seconds apart, but I&amp;rsquo;d even more rather&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; P1 and P2 finish 1 second apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address this, we need some kind of way of assigning value to each position, with better finishing positions being assigned a higher value. Sadly no such thing exists, so I&amp;rsquo;m just going to make up an arbitrary system where P1 is awarded 50 points, P2 is awarded 40 points, and subsequent positions are awarded further decreasing points until any car finishing 25th or worse receives exactly 5 points. (OK fine I stole the idea from the &lt;em&gt;Pts&lt;/em&gt; column of the results data, whatever that means). For each Position at Stake as described above, I&amp;rsquo;ll calculate &lt;strong&gt;Points at Stake&lt;/strong&gt; by determining the base point value (not bonus points) of any Position at Stake. So if P1 and P2 finish 2.3 seconds apart, that is a Points At Stake of 50. We can then get Points at Stake for an entire era by taking total Points at Stake as a percentage of total points available (Points at Stake %). This will help us estimate how competitive the racing is - but weighted by the value of the positiosn being battled over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, explanation over, here are the numbers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Period&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;At Stake %&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: right"&gt;Points at Stake %&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;OEM Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;46.3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;58.0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spec Aero&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;43.3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;55.0%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Aeroscreen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;48.6%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;61.2%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hybrid&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;48.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: right"&gt;61.8%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another win for the heavy cars and the Hybrid Era especially. During these 2 eras, more cars finished within 3 seconds of the car in front and those position battles were often towards the front of the pack where more points are awarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="conclusions"&gt;Conclusions
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve now looked at a variety of metrics that capture competitive racing and they all seem to point to the same thing. Whether its simply the gap between P1 and P2, a car&amp;rsquo;s ability to move through the field, or the number of cars finishing within striking distance of the car in front, it does seem that the heavier cars - and especially the cars with the hybrid power unit - have resulted in more competitive racing.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the hybrid is perfect. I&amp;rsquo;ve already highlighted the issues with attrition which should not be ignored. The old engine may have sounded better, and a lighter car might look faster on TV. Maybe you like watching a driver dominate a race and you want more breakawy victories. There are endless reasons why fans watch racing besides overtaking and wheel-to-wheel action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it does seem like IndyCar fans are really proud of having &lt;a class="link" href="https://x.com/wbuxtonofficial/status/1880000721833312297" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;the greatest racing on earth&lt;/a&gt;. The numbers are telling us that heavier cars - perhaps too heavy of cars - are a part of that. That may not make the hybrid an unqualified success, but it does feel like time we change the narrative a little and recognize that the hybrid is giving us some good racing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover photo by &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/@srz" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;sydney Rae&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/photos/two-race-cars-speed-around-a-curved-track-fuUDSlf3gOY" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are up with your semi-recent technical history you&amp;rsquo;re probably saying to me right now &amp;ldquo;Hey idiot, why don&amp;rsquo;t you just start at the beginning of the DW12 era in 2012?&amp;rdquo; Good point. But sadly, the &lt;a class="link" href="https://IndyCar.com/results" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m using here isn&amp;rsquo;t complete until 2013, so I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to accurately summarize those first 3 seasons for an apples-to-apples comparison with the other eras.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shout out to &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLUXSZMIiUfFSCYW1o-4whWtepyVlsfuCC" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Jon Bois&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s definitely not a phrase.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m by no means an engineering expert, so I can&amp;rsquo;t say with any certainty why this might be. One reasonable explanation is that weight is a form of downforce that isn&amp;rsquo;t subject to dirty air, so a heavy car might actually have more ability to closely follow the car in front without losing too much grip on the corners. Or it could be that heavier cars are slower and have less ability to break away in clean air. I&amp;rsquo;m sure you have your own theory.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink"&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Welcome to motorStats.io</title><link>http://localhost:1313/posts/welcome/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/welcome/</guid><description>&lt;img src="http://localhost:1313/posts/welcome/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Welcome to motorStats.io" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;motorStats.io is a new site aiming to bring the analytics revolution we&amp;rsquo;ve seen in stick-and-ball sports to IndyCar. Our goal is to provide in-depth analysis and create advanced metrics that help fans better understand what&amp;rsquo;s happening on race day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="who-is-behind-this"&gt;Who is behind this?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi, I’m Pete Melgren. I spent my 20s obsessed with advanced baseball statistics (sabermetrics) and even worked in a Major League Baseball front office doing advanced research and applied analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward a decade, and I now find myself tuning into multiple motorsports events every week, trying desperately to understand them in the same way I understand baseball. What I found is that this kind of analytical framework doesn’t really exist in the same way—at least not for IndyCar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, IndyCar makes a tremendous amount of data publicly available. So I decided to do my own research (a phrase associated with zero bad things) and see if I couldn’t gain a better understanding of IndyCar—for myself and for fellow fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="but-doesnt-motorsports-already-have-all-the-data"&gt;But doesn’t motorsports already have all the data?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;What? Why does that matter? Shut up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="but-seriously-what-is-this-site-adding"&gt;But seriously, what is this site adding?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the data work inside IndyCar is focused on engineering: building a faster race car. For fans, however, the data doesn’t (yet) answer many of the sporting or competitive questions we also care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t have great metrics for driver performance, car quality, or in-race context (like expected win probability on a given lap). Just go read a site like &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.fangraphs.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;fangraphs&lt;/a&gt; and tell me—honestly—that this kind of analysis wouldn’t be fun to have during a race or to dig into afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-should-we-expect-from-motorstatsio"&gt;What should we expect from motorStats.io?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;To start, my goal is simply to publish occasional posts that provide new and interesting context—things fans didn’t know or couldn’t easily see before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-term, I’d love for this site to grow into something more regular, possibly hosting its own database of advanced statistics and analytical tools. But that’s not something I’ll be able to do alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="this-is-cool-how-can-i-be-involved"&gt;This is cool. How can I be involved?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in being involved, please reach out—especially if you’re an IndyCar fan with a general interest in sports analytics. I&amp;rsquo;d love to collaborate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="i-think-analytics-are-terrible-and-i-wish-you-would-stop-ruining-my-sport"&gt;I think analytics are terrible and I wish you would stop ruining my sport
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you feel that way, please go watch &lt;em&gt;Moneyball&lt;/em&gt;. Not because it’ll change your mind—it probably won’t, and frankly some of those scouts had good points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, go watch &lt;em&gt;Moneyball&lt;/em&gt; because Brad Pitt gives an unreal performance, and we sometimes don’t appreciate his acting ability because he’s so damn handsome. Then, hopefully by the end of the movie, you’ll have forgotten whatever on this website made you mad and will be able to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cover photo by &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/@credwood" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Colin redwood&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="link" href="https://unsplash.com/photos/race-cars-speed-around-a-track-during-an-indy-500-Q9r_cmRqYEI" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>